Register of the Paul Robert Hanna Papers, 1920-1997
Hoover Institution Archives
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1926-1976 and undated. (Box 10.A-V)
  - Album of prints depicting P. Hanna's trip to Europe, 1926 - Returned to Family (Folder fT)
  - Album depicting dinner given by Darrel Peterson, chairman of Scott, Foresman and Co., marking P. Hanna's 45 years of service,1975 - Returned to Family (Folder fU)
  - Album depicting Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Organization banquet, April 1971 - Returned to Family (Folder fV)
  - 2 prints depicting the Pearce Mitchell Condominium dedication and P. Hanna, 30-Apr-1976 (Folder W)
  - 26 prints depicting P. Hanna, the editorial staff of World Book Encyclopedia, and other individuals and groups, 1960s (Folder X)
  - Framed print of Paul Hanna, undated (Folder Art rack: 20 front)
- INCREMENT OF MARCH 1985
  - SUBJECT FILE, 1941-1954
    - American Council on Education, Latin America film project, 1943-44 (Box-folder 140: 1)
    - American Legion Auxiliary questionnaire, 1943-44 (Folder 140: 2)
    - American Red Cross, rehabilitation training, 1943 (Folder 140: 2A)
    - American Society of Planning Officials, Committee on Education, 1941 (Folder 140: 2B)
    - Army map service (Folder 140: 3)
    - Army Specialized Training Division (ASTD)
      - Engineering (Folder 140: 4)
      - Pre-professional (Folder 140: 5)
    - Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP)
      - Correspondence, 1943-44 (Folder 140: 6-7)
      - American engineers (Folder 140: 7A)
      - Basic engineers (Folder 140: 7B)
      - Foreign Area and Language Studies (FALS)
        - Correspondence, 1943 (Folder 140: 7C)
        - European (Folder 140: 8)
        - Far Eastern (Box-folder 141: 1-2)
        - Pre-professional (Folder 141: 3)
        - 9L (Folder 141: 4)
        - Reserve program (Folder 141: 5)
    - Board of Economic Welfare (BEW) (Peru) (Folder 141: 6)
    - Bolivian education, 1943 (Folder 141: 7)
    - Bureau of Reclamation, power lines, 1943 (Folder 141: 8)
    - Campus defense, spring 1942 (Folder 141: 9)
    - Central Valley Project
      - General (Folder 141: 10-12)
      - California Housing and Planning (Folder 141: 13)
      - Part I, Significance of the Problem (Box-folder 142: 1)
    - Chinese (Folder 142: 2)
    - Civil Affairs Specialists Training Program (Folder 142: 3)
    - Civil Affairs Training School (CATS), Europe (Folder 142: 4)
    - Commission on Resources and Education (Folder 142: 5)
    - Committee on Community Survey of Child Welfare (Folder 142: 6)
    - Committee on University Services (Folder 142: 7)
    - Curriculum for Planners (Folder 142: 8)
    - Deferment from Selective Service (Folder 142: 9)
    - Electron Optics (Marton, L.) (Folder 142: 10)
    - European Area and Language School, ASTP, War Department (Folder 142: 11)
    - European Civil Affairs Specialists, Provost Marshall General's Office (PMGO), War Department (Folder 142: 12)
    - Expenses (Folder 142: 13)
    - Faculty
      - Additional teaching fields (Folder 142: 14)
      - Pool (Folder 142: 15)
    - Far East Civil Affairs Specialists (Folder 142: 16)
    - Far Eastern Area and Language School, ASTP, War Department (Folder 142: 17)
    - Foreign Area and Language Study, ASTP (Folder 142: 18)
    - Foreign Area and Language and Civil Affairs Specialists, correspondence, War Department (Folder 142: 19)
    - Foundations and gifts (Folder 142: 20)
    - Guatemala, Tropical Disease Report (Box-folder 143: 1)
    - Guggenheim Foundation (Folder 143: 2)
    - Hanna archival exchange, 7/1/82 (Folder 143: 3)
    - High Voltage Laboratory, Stanford University (Folder 143: 4)
    - Illumination Laboratory, Stanford University (Folder 143: 5)
    - Institute for Educational Interpretation (Jacobs, Harold) (Folder 143: 6)
    - Institute on Educational Reconstruction in Central and Eastern Europe, New York University, April 7-8, 1963 (Folder 143: 7)
    - Institute of Pacific Relations (Duke Pacific Institute) (Folder 143: 8)
    - Inter-American Affairs (Folder 143: 9)
    - International Cooperation Administration (ICA), new contract (Folder 143: 10)
    - Japanese Language Unit, Signal Corps, ASTD (Folder 143: 11)
    - Kellogg Foundation, Postwar planning, School of Education (Folder 143: 12)
    - Latin American Trading Center (Folder 143: 13)
    - Maritime Commission (Folder 143: 14)
    - Materials for August 24, 1942 (Stanford Resources for Public Service) (Folder 143: 15)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
      - Stanford (Folder 143: 16)
      - Washington, D.C. (Folder 143: 17)
    - National Manpower Council, New York, February 7-8, 1954 (Folder 143: 18)
    - Navy testing, 1943 (Box-folder 144: 1)
    - Office of Provost Marshall General, Civil Affairs Training Specialists (Folder 144: 2)
    - Office of Scientific Research and Development (OSRD); Baumberger, Percy; Physiology (Folder 144: 3)
    - Office of Strategic Services (OSS)
      - General (Folder 144: 4)
      - Far Eastern research (Folder 144: 5)
      - Project #1, Food in Germany (Folder 144: 6)
    - Office of War Information, foreign rehabilitation (Folder 144: 7)
    - Overseas Service
      - Government departments (Folder 144: 8)
      - Wallace Committee (Folder 144: 9)
    - Personnel Psychology
      - General (Folder 144: 10)
      - 9P, ASTP (Folder 144: 11)
    - Pool of possible Personnel Military Government, ASTP (Folder 144: 12)
    - Pre-flight Aeronautics Course, 1943 (Folder 144: 13)
    - Proposal for Stanford College, 1943 (Folder 144: 14)
    - Proposed Advanced School Public Service (Folder 144: 15)
    - Proposed Inter-American Center (Folder 144: 16)
    - Proposed Survey of San Francisco Bay Area, 1942 (Folder 144: 17)
    - Public Buildings Administration (Folder 144: 18)
    - Radar School (Folder 144: 19)
    - Regional Planning (Folder 144: 20)
    - Rehabilitation Program
      - 1 (Folder 144: 21)
      - 2 (Folder 144: 22)
    - Report on Germany (Box-folder 145: 1)
    - Roosevelt, Mrs., Office of Civilian Defense (OCD), proposals (Folder 145: 2)
    - ROTC, ASTD, Quartermaster (Folder 145: 3)
    - Ryan Laboratory (Folder 145: 4)
    - School for Labor Leaders (Folder 145: 4A)
    - Science Mobilization Bill (Folder 145: 5)
    - SPARS (Folder 145: 6)
    - State Department
      - Foreign Relief and Rehabilitation (Folder 145: 7)
      - Hoover Library (Folder 145: 8)
    - Testing Program, ASTD (Folder 145: 9)
    - Tropical Diseases Survey (Folder 145: 10)
    - University services (Folder 145: 11)
    - WACS
      - General (Folder 145: 12)
      - Physical therapy (Folder 145: 13)
    - War-Army Institute (Folder 145: 14)
    - War Department, Military Government source materials (Folder 145: 15)
    - War Manpower Commission (WMC), California Professional and Technical Survey (Folder 145: 16)
    - War Production Board, Office of Production Research and Development (Folder 145: 17)
    - Washington, D.C.
      - General (Folder 145: 18)
      - Correspondence, 1943-45 (Folder 145: 19)
    - What other universities are doing that is similar (Folder 145: 20)
    - Who's Who in Latin America (Box-folder 146: 1-2)
    - Printed matter
    - Printed matter (Box 147-148)
    - Printed matter (Box 149)
  - SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1928-1979
    - "Readings in Methods of Social Change,", n.d. (Folder 149: 1)
      Typescript (mimeographed copy).
    - The Need of Further School Accommodations in Pleasantville, New York, New York, 1928. (Folder 149: 2)
      Printed copy.
    - Arithmetic Problem Solving, New York, 1929. (Folder 149: 3)
    - "Methods of Arithmetic Problem Solving," reprint, The Mathematics Teacher, November 1930. (Folder 149: 4)
      Printe copy.
    - Wonder Flights of Long Ago, New York, London, 1930. (Folder 149: 5)
    - "The Activity Program in the Intermediate Grades," reprint, Education, April 1932. (Folder 149: 6)
    - Lincoln School Research Studies, Partial Catalog of Units of Work Activities, Projects, Themes, Etc., Columbia University, 1932. (Folder 149: 7)
    - "Readings in Methods of Social Change,", 1932. (Box-folder 150: 1)
    - "Reorganization of Social Studies," article, University of Virginia Record Extension Series, Vol. XVII, No. 4, October 1932. (Folder 150: 2)
    - Report of an Investigation of the Academic Work of the Staunton Military Academy, December 1933. (Folder 150: 3)
      Typescript (carbon copy).
    - "Social Studies Contribute to American Reconstruction," editorial, The Clearing House, Vol. IX, No. 1, 1934. (Folder 150: 4)
    - "Our Social-Economic Situation and the New Education," committee report, The Journal of Educational Sociology, May 1934. (Folder 150: 5)
    - "Social Studies in the New Virginia Curriculum," article, Progressive Education, January-February 1934. (Folder 150: 6)
    - Tentative Course of Study for Virginia Elementary Schools, 1934. (Folder 150: 7)
    - "Functional Social Studies, A Symposium, A Proposal For a Social Studies Curriculum For the Secondary Schools," reprint, California Journal of Secondary Education, October 1935. (Folder 150: 8)
    - "Romance or Reality: A Curriculum Problem," reprint, Progressive Education, May 1935. (Box-folder 151: 1)
    - "Master Teachers and Modern Education," article, California Journal of Elementary Education, Vol. IV, No. 2, November 1935. (Folder 151: 2)
    - "Future of Education," speech, Stanford Illustrated Review, January 1936. (Folder 151: 3)
    - "New Developments in Kindergarten - Primary Curriculum," speech, National Education Association Convention, June 30, 1936. (Folder 151: 4)
    - "Developing a Sequence With Social Rootage," reprint, California Journal of Secondary Education, October 1936. (Folder 151: 5)
    - Education in Wartime and After, New York, London, 1936. (Folder 151: 5A)
    - "The Evaluation of Spelling Textbooks," reprint, Educational Progress Bulletin, Vol. II, No. 3, 1936. (Folder 151: 6)
    - Youth Serves Community, New York, London, 1936. (Folder 151: 7)
    - "The Challenge to Educational Leadership," article, The Education Digest, February 1937. (Folder 151: 8)
    - "Social Education for Childhood," article, Childhood Education, Vol. XIV, No. 2, October 1937. (Folder 151: 9)
    - "Community-Curriculum Stressed at Secondary Principals Conference," speech, December 1937. (Folder 151: 9A)
    - "Training Educators for the Modern World," Stanford School of Education, 1937. (Folder 151: 10)
    - "What Is a Modern School?" speech, 1937. (Folder 151: 11)
      Typescript.
    - "Wasting America's Youth," review of How Fare American American Youth? by Homer T. Rainey, Educational Trends, February-March 1938. (Folder 151: 12)
    - Report of the Resolutions Committee, presented to the Progressive Education Association, 1938 (March 23-26), National Conference, New York City. (Folder 151: 13)
      Printed copies (in duplicate) and photocopy.
    - "Teacher Participation in Curriculum Making," speech, The National Elementary Principal, Vol. XVII, No. 5, April 1938. (Box-folder 152: 1)
    - "The Community Challenges the School," article, The Bulletin of the Michigan Secondary School Association, Vol. 2, No. 2, May 1938. (Folder 152: 2)
    - "Accepting New Civil Responsibilities," article, Character Citizenship, Vol. 5, No. 8, April 1939. (Folder 152: 3)
    - "Editorials - Providing Significant Experiences in Science," article, Childhood Education, Vol. XV, No. 8, April 1939. (Folder 152: 4)
    - The Role of Education in Utilizing Regional Resources - A Preliminary Report, Progressive Education Association, 1939. (Folder 152: 5)
    - "The Role of the School in Community Development," speech, Ohio University, March 1940. (Folder 152: 6)
      Transcription (typewritten copy).
    - Confidential Materials for Members of Commission, Commission on Resources and Education, a proposal, August 6, 1940. (Folder 152: 7)
    - Ten Communities, 1940. (Folder 152: 8)
    - "Pacific Northwest - Regional Teachers College," Hanna class project, 1940. (Folder 152: 9)
    - Confidential Report to Council of National Defense, Coordinator of Commercial and Cultural Relations Between the Americas, March 17, 1941. (Folder 152: 10)
      Typescript (carbon copy) and relevant correspondence included.
    - Masters, Hugh B., "A Community School Camp," reprint, The Elementary School Journal, XLI, No. 10, June 1941. (Folder 152: 11)
    - "Educational Relations in the Western Hemisphere," address before the National Education Association, Boston, July 1, 1941. (Folder 152: 12)
    - "Civics and Statecraft," article, Sierra Educational News, October 1941. (Folder 152: 13)
    - "My Country "Tis of Thee," review of The Use and Abuse of Natural Resources by Lucy S. Mitchell, The American Teacher, November 1941. (Folder 152: 14)
      Printed copy
    - "Pertinent Problems in School-Community Relationships," article, Childhood Education, November 1941. (Folder 152: 15)
    - "Post-Defense Planning for Children and Youth," study, National Resources Planning Board, Youth Section, December 1, 1941. (Box-folder 153: 1)
    - "Post-War Planning for Children and Youth," National Resources Development Report, January 1942. (Folder 153: 2)
    - "Capitalizing Educational Resources of the Community," speech, American Association of School Administrators, San Francisco, February 25, 1942. (Folder 153: 2A)
      Typescript with handwritten annotations.
    - "The Classroom - A Defense Unit," article, The Journal of Educational Sociology, February 1942. (Folder 153: 3)
    - Confidential Report to the Director, Educational Section of the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, Office of Emergency Management, Office of the President of the United States of America, March 10, 1942. (Folder 153: 4)
      Typescripts (carbon copies). Ten copies.
    - "Coordination and Strengthening Efforts for Children on a National Basis," speech, Association for Childhood Education, Buffalo, April 8, 1942. (Folder 153: 4A)
      Typescript with annotations. Included are clippings, correspondence, etc., pertaining to the speech.
    - "A Toast to the Future," speech, A.C.E. banquet, Buffalo, New York, April 9, 1942. (Folder 153: 5)
    - "This Hemispheric Problem," reprint, School and Society, Vol. 55, No. 1426, April 25, 1942. (Folder 153: 6)
    - "Capitalizing Educational Resources of the Community," article, The National Elementary Principal, Vol. XXI, No. 4, April 1942. (Folder 153: 7)
    - "The Right to Rest, Recreation and Adventure," article, Frontiers of Democracy, Vol. 8, No. 70, May 15, 1942. (Folder 153: 8)
      Printed copies (in duplicate).
    - Kandel, I., "Professor Hanna and the Hemispheric Problem," letter, School and Society, Vol. 55, No. 1430, May 23, 1942. (Folder 153: 9)
    - "Toward a World Community," article, Childhood Education, Vol. 19, No. 1, September 1942. (Folder 153: 10)
    - "Proposed Curriculum Procedures for Japanese Relocation Centers," Hanna course, 1942. (Folder 153: 11)
    - Washburne, Carleton, "Notes on a South American Trip," School and Society, Vol. 57, No. 1463, January 9, 1943. (Folder 153: 12)
    - Review of Cities Are for People by Mel Scott, National Municipal Review, Vol. 32, No. 5, May 1943. (Folder 153: 13)
    - "The Changing World - The Task Overdue," article, Educational Leadership, Vol I, No. 1, October 1943. (Folder 153: 14)
    - "The Changing World - These Air-Conditioned Youngsters," article, Educational Leadership, Vol I, No. 2, November 1943. (Folder 153: 15)
    - Time article on P. Hanna, Vol. XLII, No. 20, November 15, 1943. (Folder 153: 16)
    - "The Changing World - The Attack on the Three R's," article, Educational Leadership, Vol. I, No. 3, December 1943. (Folder 153: 17)
    - "The Attack on the Three R's," article, The Education Digest, Vol. IX, No. 5, January 1944. (Box-folder 154: 1)
    - "The Changing World - The Schools and Community Planning," article, Educational Leadership, Vol. I, No. 4, January 1944. (Folder 154: 2)
    - "The Changing World - In Union There Is Strength" article, Educational Leadership, Vol. I., No. 5, February 1944. (Folder 154: 3)
    - "The Changing World - When Johnny Helped the Village Smithy," article, Educational Leadership, Vol. I, No. 6, March 1944. (Folder 154: 4)
    - "The Changing World - Empty Shelves in the Earth's Storehouse," article, Educational Leadership, Vol. I, No. 7, April 1944. (Folder 154: 5)
    - "The Changing World," article, Educational Leadership, Vol. I, No. 8, May 1944. (Folder 154: 6)
    - "Are Hanna's Readers the McGuffeys of Tomorrow?" article, The Rattle of Thera Chi, June 1944. (Folder 154: 7)
    - "Children Learn of the Work, Wealth, and Happiness of Mankind," article, School Briefs, Vol. 8, No. 2, October 1944. (Folder 154: 8)
    - "Children and the Family Group," article, Primary Activities, Vol. 9, No. 2, November 1944. (Folder 154: 9)
      Photocopy.
    - "Children Learn of the Work of Mankind," article, Middle-Grade Activities, Vol. 9, No. 2, November 1944. (Folder 154: 10)
    - "Manpower For California Schools," study, State of California, January 1945. (Folder 154: 11)
    - "Alumni Newsletter," Stanford University School of Education, Vol. 3, No. 2, March 1945. (Folder 154: 11A)
    - "The Effect of the Central Valley Project On the Agricultural and Industrial Economy and On the Social Character of California," report, March 1945. (Folder 154: 12-13)
    - Reports of Committees and Proposal for a California Council on Teacher Education, Work Council on Teacher Education, California State Department Education, May 1945. (Folder 154: 14)
    - "A Stanford Pacific Institute," study, May 1945. (Folder 154: 15)
      Typescript (photocopy).
    - "Primary Curriculum Survey, 1944-45," A Scott-Foresman Research Bulletin, Spring 1945. (Folder 154: 16)
    - "Educational Planning - Continued Education of Teachers," article, The School Executive, Vol. 65, No. 2, October 1945. (Folder 154: 17)
    - "Education and Community Planning," article, Community Planning for Peacetime Living, Stanford, 1945. (Box-folder 155: 1)
    - "Education for the Larger Community," article, Educational Leadership, Vol. IV, No. 1, October 1946. (Folder 155: 2)
    - "Education for an Air World," reprint, Air Affairs, December 1946. (Folder 155: 3)
    - "The Nation Reports," article, The National Elementary Principal, Vol. 26, No. 3, December 1946. (Folder 155: 4)
    - Aviation Education Source Book, Stanford University School of Education, New York, 1946. (Folder 155: 5)
    - Report of the United States Education Mission to Germany, U.S. Government Printing Office, Washington, D.C., 1946. (Folder 155: 6)
    - "The Nation Reports," article, The National Elementary Principal, Vol. 26, No. 4, February 1947. (Folder 155: 7)
    - "What the World Community Demands of German Education," study for OMGUS, April 1947. (Folder 155: 8)
    - "Techniques for Utilizing Community Resources," article, The Elementary School in the Community, 1947. (Folder 155: 9)
    - "Youth Shares in Planning a Better Philadelphia," P. Hanna served as consultant to Philadelphia Public Schools, 1947. (Folder 155: 10)
    - "The European Campus for the American Way in Education," Annual Conference of the California Association of Public School Superintendents, Proceedings, January 1948. (Folder 155: 11)
    - "News From the Field - Far Western States," article, The National Elementary Principal, Vol. 27, No. 5, April 1948. (Folder 155: 12)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica Films, Inc., "Airport," with Helen Clifford Gunter, June 16, 1948. (Folder 155: 13)
    - "What Makes a Good Elementary School - From the Standpoint of Supervision?" panel discussion, The National Elementary Principal, Vol. 27, No. 6, June 1948. (Folder 155: 14)
    - "Preparing For Careers in Education," School of Education Stanford University Bulletin, December 1948. (Box-folder 156: 1)
    - "Introduction," reprint, Air Affairs, Winter 1948. (Folder 156: 2)
    - California Legislature, Senate Investigating Committee on Education, Building America, 1948. (Folder 156: 3)
      Printed matter.
    - UNESCO Educational Missions, Report of the Mission to the Philippines, July 1949. (Folder 156: 4)
      3 printed copies, 1 printed copy in French.
    - A Report of the National Conference on Community School Camping, Highland Recreation Area, Michigan, September 26-28, 1949. (Folder 156: 5)
    - "What Schools Are For," article, The School Executive, January 1950. (Folder 156: 6)
    - "The Educational Outlook at Mid-Century," article
      - Alabama School Journal, February 1950. (Folder 156: 7)
      - Delaware School Journal, February 1950. (Folder 156: 8)
      - The Journal of Arkansas Education, February 1950. (Folder 156: 9)
      - Wisconsin Journal of Education, February 1950. (Folder 156: 10)
      - The Kansas Teacher, February 1950. (Folder 156: 11)
      - Montana Education, February 1950. (Folder 156: 12)
      - The Texas Outlook, February 1950. (Folder 156: 13)
    - "Changes in Society That Call for Changes in Education," article, Educational Outlook, Vol. 24, No. 3, March 1950. (Folder 156: 14)
    - "The Educational Outlook at Mid-Century," article
      - Louisiana Schools, March 1950. (Folder 156: 15)
      - Virginia Journal of Education, March 1950. (Folder 156: 16)
    - "Geography and the Nine-Year-Olds," article, School Briefs, March 1950. (Folder 156: 17)
    - "The Educational Outlook at Mid-Century," article, The Educational Review, April 1950. (Folder 156: 18)
    - "The UNESCO Educational Survey," Philippine Journal of Education, April 1950. (Folder 156: 19)
    - "Using the April Calendar Picture," Primary Activities, April-May 1950. (Folder 156: 20)
    - "Education Rides the Atom," article, New Hampshire Educator, May 1950. (Folder 156: 21)
    - "The Educational Outlook at Mid-Century," article
      - Georgia Education Journal, May 1950. (Folder 156: 22)
      - Utah Educational Review, May 1950. (Folder 156: 23)
    - "SF Comes Across With Cross-Country, New Geography Textbook for Grade Four," article, School Briefs, May 1950. (Folder 156: 24)
    - "The Shape of Things to Come," article, North Carolina Education, May 1950. (Folder 156: 25)
    - "The Philippines - Meeting of East and West," article, The Pacific Spectator, Spring 1950. (Folder 156: 26)
    - "Famous Speakers at This Year's Convention," article on KSTA Convention, The Kansas Teacher, October 1950. (Box-folder 157: 1)
    - Renner, George, "The Baby That Became a Giant -Geography," article, Michigan Education Journal, October 1950. (Folder 157: 2)
    - "The Three R's Have Changed," article, The School Executive, October 1950. (Folder 157: 3)
    - Air Affairs, December 1950. (Folder 157: 4)
    - "Red-Educators at University of California, Stanford University, California Institute of Technology," National Council for American Education, 1950. (Folder 157: 5)
    - "Technical Training and General Education," Third Stanford Conference on Latin America, June 18-20, 1951. (Folder 157: 6)
    - "Elementary Education in 1975," Eleventh National Conference, National Education Association, Asilomar, California, July 9-20, 1951. (Folder 157: 7)
    - "What the Future in Education?" article, The Saskatchewan Bulletin, September 1951. (Folder 157: 8)
    - "Needed Research on Textbooks," article, The Phi Delta Kappan, January 1952. (Folder 157: 9)
    - "The School and the Future of Mankind," article
      - The BC Teacher, January 1952. (Folder 157: 10)
      - The Journal of Arkansas Education, January 1952. (Folder 157: 11)
      - SDEA Journal, January 1952. (Folder 157: 12)
        Printed copies (2)
      - Wisconsin Journal of Education, January 1952. (Folder 157: 13)
      - The Oklahoma Teacher, February 1952. (Folder 157: 14)
      - Georgia Education Journal, February 1952. (Folder 157: 15)
        Clipping.